<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving
and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">

<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">

<front>


<article-meta>


<title-group>
<article-title>Draft Report</article-title>
</title-group>

<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Cooper</surname>
<given-names>Mckenna</given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Mckenna Cooper</string-name>

<role vocab="https://credit.niso.org" vocab-term="writing – original
draft" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">writing</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor-1">&#x002A;</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sarah</surname>
<given-names></given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Sarah</string-name>

<role vocab="https://credit.niso.org" vocab-term="writing – original
draft" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">writing</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Archer</surname>
<given-names></given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Archer</string-name>

<role vocab="https://credit.niso.org" vocab-term="writing – original
draft" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">writing</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">a</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Colorado State University</institution>
</institution-wrap>







</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor-1"></corresp>
</author-notes>









<history></history>






</article-meta>

</front>

<body>
<sec id="rivers-and-lakes-bring-the-boys-to-the-yard-assessing-the-effect-of-riparian-zones-on-taxonomic-richness">
  <title>Rivers and Lakes Bring the Boys to the Yard: Assessing the
  Effect of Riparian Zones on Taxonomic Richness</title>
  <sec id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <p>Throughout the mythologies of ancient civilizations, rivers are
    often portrayed as sacred lifelines and mystical forces that breathe
    life into the land. From the Nile of Egypt to the Ganges in India,
    rivers shaped the very foundation of human development. The route a
    river carves through a landscape not only guides the path of its
    water, but also dictates the types of vegetation that grow alongside
    it, the diversity of animals that depend on it, and the feasibility
    of long-term human settlement. The majority of the world’s great
    cities were born beside rivers, not merely for commerce, which could
    be achieved from any coast, but for one elemental advantage: rivers
    carry fresh water. Drinkable water. Or at least, they used to. In
    today’s world, the demand for freshwater is greater than ever.
    Global population growth, expanding agricultural demands, urban
    sprawl, and climate change are placing unprecedented stress on
    aquatic ecosystems. Historically, human progress has been closely
    tied to our ability to manipulate the quantity of water available
    through irrigation systems, dams, aqueducts, and other technologies.
    But as environmental pressures grow, we are now forced to reckon
    with a second, equally critical dimension: water quality. Just as
    our ancestors learned to interpret the presence of certain plants
    and animals as signs of viable water sources, modern ecologists use
    biological indicators to evaluate the health of freshwater systems.
    Among the most widely used of these indicators are benthic
    macroinvertebrates; organisms that live on the bottom of rivers,
    lakes, and streams and include insects, crustaceans, mollusks, and
    worms. These organisms are uniquely valuable for biomonitoring due
    to their varied tolerance to pollutants, their limited mobility
    (which ties them to local conditions), and their life cycles, which
    span seasons or years. One particularly important group of
    macroinvertebrates used to indicate good water quality is the EPT
    taxa; Ephemeroptera (mayflies), Plecoptera (stoneflies), and
    Trichoptera (caddisflies). These taxa are generally sensitive to
    environmental disturbances, and their presence in high abundance is
    often correlated with clean, well-oxygenated water. In contrast, a
    dominance of more pollution-tolerant organisms such as oligochaete
    worms, leeches, and midge larvae (Chironomidae) is typically a sign
    of poor water quality and habitat degradation (McDonald, Mullins,
    and Lewis, 1991). However, water quality is not influenced solely by
    what occurs within the streambed. The surrounding environment,
    particularly riparian zones, plays a critical role. Riparian zones
    are the transitional areas between terrestrial and aquatic
    ecosystems, typically encompassing the vegetation and soils adjacent
    to rivers and streams. Though narrow in spatial extent, riparian
    zones provide disproportionate ecological benefits. They act as
    natural buffers, filtering out sediments, nutrients, and pollutants
    before they reach the water body. They also stabilize stream banks,
    reduce erosion, moderate water temperature through shading, and
    provide crucial habitat for a wide range of terrestrial and aquatic
    organisms. As such, the integrity of riparian zones is often used as
    a secondary, yet equally important, indicator of watershed health
    (Sabo et al., 2005). Unfortunately, riparian zones are frequently
    the first casualties of human development. Agricultural expansion,
    urbanization, logging, and road construction often involve the
    removal or fragmentation of riparian vegetation. When riparian zones
    are degraded, their ability to support both terrestrial and aquatic
    biodiversity diminishes, and the systems they protect become more
    vulnerable to pollution, sedimentation, and thermal stress.
    Consequently, monitoring the type and abundance of riparian
    vegetation can yield valuable insights into the overall ecological
    condition of a watershed, and by extension, its capacity to support
    a diverse and healthy macroinvertebrate community. With these
    connections in mind, our project seeks to investigate the
    relationship between riparian zone condition and freshwater
    invertebrate diversity. Specifically, we aim to evaluate whether the
    composition and abundance of riparian plant cover is associated with
    the composition and abundance of benthic macroinvertebrates, with an
    emphasis on EPT taxa as indicators of ecosystem health. By exploring
    these patterns, we hope to contribute to a better understanding of
    how human land use and vegetation management practices may impact
    water quality through both direct and indirect ecological pathways.
    To conduct this analysis, we will use data from the Klamath Network
    Lakes Monitoring Data Package (2013–2019), which includes biological
    and ecological monitoring data collected across three national
    parks: Crater Lake, Lassen Volcanic, and Redwood National Parks.
    From this dataset, we will focus on three specific tables:
    InvertSpecies.csv, which documents the abundance of
    macroinvertebrates at various sampling plots, RiparianCover.csv,
    which describes the vegetation characteristics of corresponding
    riparian zones, and WaterQuality.csv which includes data on physical
    and chemical water parameters at each sampling plot. Integrating
    this dataset will allow us to account for potential covariates or
    confounding variables, such as dissolved oxygen, pH, or turbidity,
    that may influence macroinvertebrate populations independently of
    vegetation conditions. Using this data, we will assign a
    standardized “vegetation score” to each plot based on the richness
    and type of plant cover recorded. This score will serve as a proxy
    for riparian zone quality. We will then analyze the relationship
    between this vegetation score and macroinvertebrate diversity,
    particularly the presence of sensitive EPT taxa, using statistical
    methods in RStudio. To determine the strength and direction of
    relationships between variables, we will conduct correlation tests
    (Pearson or Spearman, depending on normality assumptions). To model
    the predictive influence of vegetation on macroinvertebrate
    abundance, we will use linear regression analysis. These statistical
    approaches will be complemented by clear and informative data
    visualizations created with ggplot2, including scatterplots, box
    plots, and bar graphs to communicate trends and variation across
    sites. This holistic approach will allow us to better interpret the
    ecological relationships we uncover and provide more robust insights
    into freshwater health within these protected park systems.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="data-exploration">
    <title>Data Exploration</title>
    <p>All data for this project comes from the Klamath Lakes Monitoring
    Data Package 2013–2019, originally compiled by the U.S. Department
    of the Interior and now publicly available through Data.com. This
    dataset includes ecological monitoring records from Crater Lake
    National Park (NP), Lassen Volcanic NP, and Redwood National and
    State Parks (NSP). However, for the purposes of our study, we will
    exclusively use data collected at Crater Lake National Park,
    narrowing the geographic focus to improve consistency and data
    quality. The three files central to our analysis are
    InvertSpecies.csv, RiparianCover.csv, and WaterQuality.csv. These
    files contain complementary data and share key identifying columns,
    including Lake_Code, Start_Date, and Park_Name—which will allow us
    to merge the datasets and compare biological, physical, and
    vegetative conditions at each sampled water body. The InvertSpecies
    file contains records of benthic macroinvertebrate communities
    sampled in lakes and ponds. It includes fields such as Taxon, Order,
    Count, and Life_Stage. For this study, we will focus on the orders
    Ephemeroptera (mayflies), Plecoptera (stoneflies), and Trichoptera
    (caddisflies), which are collectively known as EPT taxa. These
    macroinvertebrates are widely recognized as indicators of healthy
    freshwater ecosystems, as they are generally sensitive to pollution
    and habitat degradation. The RiparianCover file provides plot-level
    data on vegetation type and structure in riparian zones, such as
    Big_trees_ArealCover, Woody_shrubs_saplings_GroundCover,
    Canopy_Type, and Barren_AreaCcover. These variables will help us
    estimate the ecological integrity and potential human impact on
    surrounding shorelines. Each plot corresponds to a specific lake,
    allowing us to associate vegetation conditions with
    macroinvertebrate presence in those water bodies. The WaterQuality
    file offers insight into the abiotic conditions of each lake,
    including key measurements like Temperature_C, pH, Turbidity,
    Dissolved_oxygen, and Specific_conductivity. These parameters may
    contribute to or constrain macroinvertebrate diversity and could
    help contextualize any patterns observed between vegetation and
    aquatic biodiversity. While all three files have a relatively large
    number of rows (RiparianCover.csv: 1,680; InvertSpecies.csv: 3,299),
    some fields contain missing values, particularly with respect to
    sampling dates and environmental measurements. To account for this,
    we will filter for data collected in 2018, a year with strong
    representation across datasets, and group observations by plot. This
    will allow us to match vegetation conditions with corresponding
    macroinvertebrate counts and water quality measurements. From
    RiparianCover.csv, we are particularly interested in a subset of
    vegetation metrics that reflect both habitat structure and
    disturbance: Big_trees_ArealCover,
    Woody_shrubs_saplings_GroundCover, and Barren_ArealCover. These will
    form the basis of a vegetation condition score used later in the
    analysis. Meanwhile, from InvertSpecies.csv, we will extract insect
    counts and filter specifically for EPT taxa, which we define as
    “significantly present” when observed in quantities of at least 10
    individuals per plot. Lastly, WaterQuality.csv will be used to
    examine physical and chemical characteristics of each lake. These
    variables will not only support broader ecological interpretations
    but also offer an additional layer of explanatory context for
    understanding macroinvertebrate patterns. By combining these three
    datasets with consistent identifiers and a focused temporal and
    spatial scope (Crater Lake, 2018), we can begin exploring the
    relationships among riparian cover, water quality, and
    macroinvertebrate biodiversity with clarity and coherence.</p>
    <sec id="data-visualizations">
      <title>Data Visualizations</title>
      <p>Data Preparation</p>
      <p>**Note: Although it is stated above and in Preliminary Methods
      that we would only be evaluating Carter Lake National Park in the
      year 2018, this was not feasible for the drafted visualizations.
      We had to pivot to a different proposal idea due to the
      elimination of data this past weekend, and need more time to
      narrow down how to visualize with these specific data sets. 1.</p>
      <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-2-1.png" />
      <list list-type="order">
        <list-item>
          <label>2.</label>
        </list-item>
      </list>
      <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png" />
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="preliminary-methods">
    <title>Preliminary Methods</title>
    <p>To begin our analysis, we will first join the three
    datasets—InvertSpecies.csv, RiparianCover.csv, and
    WaterQuality.csv—using shared identifying columns: Lake_Code,
    Park_Name, and Start_Date. We will then filter the merged dataset to
    include only Crater Lake National Park and data collected in 2018,
    to maintain consistency in time and location. Next, we will divide
    our dataset into two groups of lakes based on the presence or
    absence of sensitive macroinvertebrate orders: Ephemeroptera,
    Plecoptera, and Trichoptera (collectively referred to as EPT taxa).
    These taxa serve as bioindicators of high water quality and intact
    riparian zones. A lake will be categorized as “EPT-present” if at
    least 10 individuals from any of the three orders are found. Lakes
    without EPT taxa or with fewer than 10 individuals will be
    categorized as “EPT-absent.” Once we have established these two
    groups, we will assess potential relationships between riparian
    vegetation characteristics and the presence of EPT taxa. Key
    vegetation variables from RiparianCover.csv will include:
    Big_trees_ArealCover</p>
    <p>Woody_shrubs_saplings_GroundCover</p>
    <p>Barren_ArealCover</p>
    <p>We will explore creating a vegetation integrity index by
    standardizing and summing Big_trees_ArealCover,
    Woody_shrubs_saplings_GroundCover, and inverse Barren_ArealCover
    scores. We will also consider select abiotic water quality variables
    from WaterQuality.csv—such as Temperature_C, pH, and
    Dissolved_oxygen—to help contextualize our findings or identify
    confounding influences. For statistical analysis, we will choose
    appropriate tests based on the type of variables being compared:</p>
    <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
        <p>For categorical comparisons (e.g., EPT presence
        vs. vegetation category), we may use a Chi-squared test.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>For numerical comparisons (e.g., EPT presence vs. percent
        vegetation cover), we will consider a T-test or ANOVA.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>If relationships appear linear, we may explore correlation
        coefficients or linear regression models to assess strength and
        direction.</p>
      </list-item>
    </list>
    <p>To support our findings, we will use ggplot2 in R to create clear
    and informative visualizations—such as boxplots, bar charts, or
    scatterplots—highlighting any significant trends or differences
    between the EPT-present and EPT-absent lake groups. Finally, missing
    data and uneven sampling will be carefully handled—either through
    exclusion of incomplete rows or imputation strategies, depending on
    the nature and extent of the gaps.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
</body>

<back>
</back>

<sub-article article-type="notebook" id="nb-4-nb-article">
<front-stub>
<title-group>
<article-title>Draft Report</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Cooper</surname>
<given-names>Mckenna</given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Mckenna Cooper</string-name>

<role vocab="https://credit.niso.org" vocab-term="writing – original
draft" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">writing</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1-nb-article">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor-1-nb-article">&#x002A;</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sarah</surname>
<given-names></given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Sarah</string-name>

<role vocab="https://credit.niso.org" vocab-term="writing – original
draft" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">writing</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1-nb-article">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Archer</surname>
<given-names></given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Archer</string-name>

<role vocab="https://credit.niso.org" vocab-term="writing – original
draft" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">writing</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1-nb-article">a</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff-1-nb-article">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Colorado State University</institution>
</institution-wrap>







</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor-1-nb-article"></corresp>
</author-notes>
</front-stub>

<body>
<sec id="rivers-and-lakes-bring-the-boys-to-the-yard-assessing-the-effect-of-riparian-zones-on-taxonomic-richness-nb-article">
  <title>Rivers and Lakes Bring the Boys to the Yard: Assessing the
  Effect of Riparian Zones on Taxonomic Richness</title>
  <sec id="introduction-nb-article">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <p>Throughout the mythologies of ancient civilizations, rivers are
    often portrayed as sacred lifelines and mystical forces that breathe
    life into the land. From the Nile of Egypt to the Ganges in India,
    rivers shaped the very foundation of human development. The route a
    river carves through a landscape not only guides the path of its
    water, but also dictates the types of vegetation that grow alongside
    it, the diversity of animals that depend on it, and the feasibility
    of long-term human settlement. The majority of the world’s great
    cities were born beside rivers, not merely for commerce, which could
    be achieved from any coast, but for one elemental advantage: rivers
    carry fresh water. Drinkable water. Or at least, they used to. In
    today’s world, the demand for freshwater is greater than ever.
    Global population growth, expanding agricultural demands, urban
    sprawl, and climate change are placing unprecedented stress on
    aquatic ecosystems. Historically, human progress has been closely
    tied to our ability to manipulate the quantity of water available
    through irrigation systems, dams, aqueducts, and other technologies.
    But as environmental pressures grow, we are now forced to reckon
    with a second, equally critical dimension: water quality. Just as
    our ancestors learned to interpret the presence of certain plants
    and animals as signs of viable water sources, modern ecologists use
    biological indicators to evaluate the health of freshwater systems.
    Among the most widely used of these indicators are benthic
    macroinvertebrates; organisms that live on the bottom of rivers,
    lakes, and streams and include insects, crustaceans, mollusks, and
    worms. These organisms are uniquely valuable for biomonitoring due
    to their varied tolerance to pollutants, their limited mobility
    (which ties them to local conditions), and their life cycles, which
    span seasons or years. One particularly important group of
    macroinvertebrates used to indicate good water quality is the EPT
    taxa; Ephemeroptera (mayflies), Plecoptera (stoneflies), and
    Trichoptera (caddisflies). These taxa are generally sensitive to
    environmental disturbances, and their presence in high abundance is
    often correlated with clean, well-oxygenated water. In contrast, a
    dominance of more pollution-tolerant organisms such as oligochaete
    worms, leeches, and midge larvae (Chironomidae) is typically a sign
    of poor water quality and habitat degradation (McDonald, Mullins,
    and Lewis, 1991). However, water quality is not influenced solely by
    what occurs within the streambed. The surrounding environment,
    particularly riparian zones, plays a critical role. Riparian zones
    are the transitional areas between terrestrial and aquatic
    ecosystems, typically encompassing the vegetation and soils adjacent
    to rivers and streams. Though narrow in spatial extent, riparian
    zones provide disproportionate ecological benefits. They act as
    natural buffers, filtering out sediments, nutrients, and pollutants
    before they reach the water body. They also stabilize stream banks,
    reduce erosion, moderate water temperature through shading, and
    provide crucial habitat for a wide range of terrestrial and aquatic
    organisms. As such, the integrity of riparian zones is often used as
    a secondary, yet equally important, indicator of watershed health
    (Sabo et al., 2005). Unfortunately, riparian zones are frequently
    the first casualties of human development. Agricultural expansion,
    urbanization, logging, and road construction often involve the
    removal or fragmentation of riparian vegetation. When riparian zones
    are degraded, their ability to support both terrestrial and aquatic
    biodiversity diminishes, and the systems they protect become more
    vulnerable to pollution, sedimentation, and thermal stress.
    Consequently, monitoring the type and abundance of riparian
    vegetation can yield valuable insights into the overall ecological
    condition of a watershed, and by extension, its capacity to support
    a diverse and healthy macroinvertebrate community. With these
    connections in mind, our project seeks to investigate the
    relationship between riparian zone condition and freshwater
    invertebrate diversity. Specifically, we aim to evaluate whether the
    composition and abundance of riparian plant cover is associated with
    the composition and abundance of benthic macroinvertebrates, with an
    emphasis on EPT taxa as indicators of ecosystem health. By exploring
    these patterns, we hope to contribute to a better understanding of
    how human land use and vegetation management practices may impact
    water quality through both direct and indirect ecological pathways.
    To conduct this analysis, we will use data from the Klamath Network
    Lakes Monitoring Data Package (2013–2019), which includes biological
    and ecological monitoring data collected across three national
    parks: Crater Lake, Lassen Volcanic, and Redwood National Parks.
    From this dataset, we will focus on three specific tables:
    InvertSpecies.csv, which documents the abundance of
    macroinvertebrates at various sampling plots, RiparianCover.csv,
    which describes the vegetation characteristics of corresponding
    riparian zones, and WaterQuality.csv which includes data on physical
    and chemical water parameters at each sampling plot. Integrating
    this dataset will allow us to account for potential covariates or
    confounding variables, such as dissolved oxygen, pH, or turbidity,
    that may influence macroinvertebrate populations independently of
    vegetation conditions. Using this data, we will assign a
    standardized “vegetation score” to each plot based on the richness
    and type of plant cover recorded. This score will serve as a proxy
    for riparian zone quality. We will then analyze the relationship
    between this vegetation score and macroinvertebrate diversity,
    particularly the presence of sensitive EPT taxa, using statistical
    methods in RStudio. To determine the strength and direction of
    relationships between variables, we will conduct correlation tests
    (Pearson or Spearman, depending on normality assumptions). To model
    the predictive influence of vegetation on macroinvertebrate
    abundance, we will use linear regression analysis. These statistical
    approaches will be complemented by clear and informative data
    visualizations created with ggplot2, including scatterplots, box
    plots, and bar graphs to communicate trends and variation across
    sites. This holistic approach will allow us to better interpret the
    ecological relationships we uncover and provide more robust insights
    into freshwater health within these protected park systems.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="data-exploration-nb-article">
    <title>Data Exploration</title>
    <p>All data for this project comes from the Klamath Lakes Monitoring
    Data Package 2013–2019, originally compiled by the U.S. Department
    of the Interior and now publicly available through Data.com. This
    dataset includes ecological monitoring records from Crater Lake
    National Park (NP), Lassen Volcanic NP, and Redwood National and
    State Parks (NSP). However, for the purposes of our study, we will
    exclusively use data collected at Crater Lake National Park,
    narrowing the geographic focus to improve consistency and data
    quality. The three files central to our analysis are
    InvertSpecies.csv, RiparianCover.csv, and WaterQuality.csv. These
    files contain complementary data and share key identifying columns,
    including Lake_Code, Start_Date, and Park_Name—which will allow us
    to merge the datasets and compare biological, physical, and
    vegetative conditions at each sampled water body. The InvertSpecies
    file contains records of benthic macroinvertebrate communities
    sampled in lakes and ponds. It includes fields such as Taxon, Order,
    Count, and Life_Stage. For this study, we will focus on the orders
    Ephemeroptera (mayflies), Plecoptera (stoneflies), and Trichoptera
    (caddisflies), which are collectively known as EPT taxa. These
    macroinvertebrates are widely recognized as indicators of healthy
    freshwater ecosystems, as they are generally sensitive to pollution
    and habitat degradation. The RiparianCover file provides plot-level
    data on vegetation type and structure in riparian zones, such as
    Big_trees_ArealCover, Woody_shrubs_saplings_GroundCover,
    Canopy_Type, and Barren_AreaCcover. These variables will help us
    estimate the ecological integrity and potential human impact on
    surrounding shorelines. Each plot corresponds to a specific lake,
    allowing us to associate vegetation conditions with
    macroinvertebrate presence in those water bodies. The WaterQuality
    file offers insight into the abiotic conditions of each lake,
    including key measurements like Temperature_C, pH, Turbidity,
    Dissolved_oxygen, and Specific_conductivity. These parameters may
    contribute to or constrain macroinvertebrate diversity and could
    help contextualize any patterns observed between vegetation and
    aquatic biodiversity. While all three files have a relatively large
    number of rows (RiparianCover.csv: 1,680; InvertSpecies.csv: 3,299),
    some fields contain missing values, particularly with respect to
    sampling dates and environmental measurements. To account for this,
    we will filter for data collected in 2018, a year with strong
    representation across datasets, and group observations by plot. This
    will allow us to match vegetation conditions with corresponding
    macroinvertebrate counts and water quality measurements. From
    RiparianCover.csv, we are particularly interested in a subset of
    vegetation metrics that reflect both habitat structure and
    disturbance: Big_trees_ArealCover,
    Woody_shrubs_saplings_GroundCover, and Barren_ArealCover. These will
    form the basis of a vegetation condition score used later in the
    analysis. Meanwhile, from InvertSpecies.csv, we will extract insect
    counts and filter specifically for EPT taxa, which we define as
    “significantly present” when observed in quantities of at least 10
    individuals per plot. Lastly, WaterQuality.csv will be used to
    examine physical and chemical characteristics of each lake. These
    variables will not only support broader ecological interpretations
    but also offer an additional layer of explanatory context for
    understanding macroinvertebrate patterns. By combining these three
    datasets with consistent identifiers and a focused temporal and
    spatial scope (Crater Lake, 2018), we can begin exploring the
    relationships among riparian cover, water quality, and
    macroinvertebrate biodiversity with clarity and coherence.</p>
    <sec id="data-visualizations-nb-article">
      <title>Data Visualizations</title>
      <p>Data Preparation</p>
      <sec specific-use="notebook-content">
      <code language="r script"># Load libraries
library(dplyr)</code>
      <boxed-text>
        <preformat>
Attaching package: 'dplyr'</preformat>
      </boxed-text>
      <boxed-text>
        <preformat>The following objects are masked from 'package:stats':

    filter, lag</preformat>
      </boxed-text>
      <boxed-text>
        <preformat>The following objects are masked from 'package:base':

    intersect, setdiff, setequal, union</preformat>
      </boxed-text>
      <code language="r script">library(ggplot2)

# Load datasets
invert_species &lt;- read.csv(&quot;InvertSpecies.csv&quot;)
riparian_cover &lt;- read.csv(&quot;RiparianCover.csv&quot;)
water_quality &lt;- read.csv(&quot;WaterQuality.csv&quot;)

# Filter for Crater Lake and 2018
invert_species_filtered &lt;- invert_species %&gt;%
  filter(Park_Name == &quot;Crater Lake National Park&quot; &amp; Start_Date &gt;= &quot;2018-01-01&quot; &amp; Start_Date &lt;= &quot;2018-12-31&quot;)

riparian_cover_filtered &lt;- riparian_cover %&gt;%
  filter(Park_Name == &quot;Crater Lake National Park&quot; &amp; Start_Date &gt;= &quot;2018-01-01&quot; &amp; Start_Date &lt;= &quot;2018-12-31&quot;)

water_quality_filtered &lt;- water_quality %&gt;%
  filter(Park_Name == &quot;Crater Lake National Park&quot; &amp; Start_Date &gt;= &quot;2018-01-01&quot; &amp; Start_Date &lt;= &quot;2018-12-31&quot;)

# Merge datasets
merged_data &lt;- invert_species_filtered %&gt;%
  inner_join(riparian_cover_filtered, by = c(&quot;Lake_Code&quot;, &quot;Park_Name&quot;, &quot;Start_Date&quot;)) %&gt;%
  inner_join(water_quality_filtered, by = c(&quot;Lake_Code&quot;, &quot;Park_Name&quot;, &quot;Start_Date&quot;))</code>
      </sec>
      <p>**Note: Although it is stated above and in Preliminary Methods
      that we would only be evaluating Carter Lake National Park in the
      year 2018, this was not feasible for the drafted visualizations.
      We had to pivot to a different proposal idea due to the
      elimination of data this past weekend, and need more time to
      narrow down how to visualize with these specific data sets. 1.</p>
      <sec specific-use="notebook-content">
      <code language="r script">invert_species %&gt;%
  filter(
    Park_Name == &quot;Crater Lake National Park&quot;,
    Start_Date &gt;= &quot;2013-01-01&quot;, Start_Date &lt;= &quot;2019-12-31&quot;,
    !is.na(Order),
    !is.na(Count)
  ) %&gt;%
  group_by(Order) %&gt;%
  summarize(Total_Count = sum(Count, na.rm = TRUE)) %&gt;%
  ggplot(aes(x = reorder(Order, -Total_Count), y = Total_Count, fill = Order)) +
  geom_col(show.legend = FALSE) +
  labs(
    title = &quot;Total Invertebrate Count by Order (Crater Lake, 2013-2019)&quot;,
    x = &quot;Invertebrate Order&quot;,
    y = &quot;Total Count&quot;
  ) +
  theme_minimal() +
  theme(axis.text.x = element_text(angle = 45, hjust = 1))</code>
      <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-2-1.png" />
      </sec>
      <list list-type="order">
        <list-item>
          <label>2.</label>
        </list-item>
      </list>
      <sec specific-use="notebook-content">
      <code language="r script"># Load necessary library
library(ggplot2)

# Create a sample dataset
data &lt;- data.frame(
  Park_Name = c(&quot;Redwood National and State Parks&quot;, &quot;Lassen Volcanic National Park&quot;, &quot;Crater Lake National Park&quot;),
  Big_Trees = c(20, 15, 30),
  Small_Trees = c(10, 20, 15),
  Understory_Veg = c(30, 25, 20),
  Woody_Shrubs_Saplings = c(15, 10, 25),
  Herb_Grass_Forb = c(25, 30, 10)
)

# Melt the data for ggplot
library(reshape2)</code>
      <boxed-text>
        <preformat>Warning: package 'reshape2' was built under R version 4.4.3</preformat>
      </boxed-text>
      <code language="r script">data_melted &lt;- melt(data, id.vars = &quot;Park_Name&quot;, 
                    variable.name = &quot;Vegetation_Type&quot;, 
                    value.name = &quot;Areal_Cover&quot;)

# Plot stacked bar chart with tilted axis labels
ggplot(data_melted, aes(x = Park_Name, y = Areal_Cover, fill = Vegetation_Type)) +
  geom_bar(stat = &quot;identity&quot;, position = &quot;stack&quot;) +
  labs(title = &quot;Riparian Vegetation Areal Cover&quot;, 
       x = &quot;Park Name&quot;, 
       y = &quot;Areal Cover (%)&quot;, 
       fill = &quot;Vegetation Type&quot;) +
  theme_minimal() +
  theme(axis.text.x = element_text(angle = 45, hjust = 1))</code>
      <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="index_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png" />
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="preliminary-methods-nb-article">
    <title>Preliminary Methods</title>
    <p>To begin our analysis, we will first join the three
    datasets—InvertSpecies.csv, RiparianCover.csv, and
    WaterQuality.csv—using shared identifying columns: Lake_Code,
    Park_Name, and Start_Date. We will then filter the merged dataset to
    include only Crater Lake National Park and data collected in 2018,
    to maintain consistency in time and location. Next, we will divide
    our dataset into two groups of lakes based on the presence or
    absence of sensitive macroinvertebrate orders: Ephemeroptera,
    Plecoptera, and Trichoptera (collectively referred to as EPT taxa).
    These taxa serve as bioindicators of high water quality and intact
    riparian zones. A lake will be categorized as “EPT-present” if at
    least 10 individuals from any of the three orders are found. Lakes
    without EPT taxa or with fewer than 10 individuals will be
    categorized as “EPT-absent.” Once we have established these two
    groups, we will assess potential relationships between riparian
    vegetation characteristics and the presence of EPT taxa. Key
    vegetation variables from RiparianCover.csv will include:
    Big_trees_ArealCover</p>
    <p>Woody_shrubs_saplings_GroundCover</p>
    <p>Barren_ArealCover</p>
    <p>We will explore creating a vegetation integrity index by
    standardizing and summing Big_trees_ArealCover,
    Woody_shrubs_saplings_GroundCover, and inverse Barren_ArealCover
    scores. We will also consider select abiotic water quality variables
    from WaterQuality.csv—such as Temperature_C, pH, and
    Dissolved_oxygen—to help contextualize our findings or identify
    confounding influences. For statistical analysis, we will choose
    appropriate tests based on the type of variables being compared:</p>
    <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
        <p>For categorical comparisons (e.g., EPT presence
        vs. vegetation category), we may use a Chi-squared test.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>For numerical comparisons (e.g., EPT presence vs. percent
        vegetation cover), we will consider a T-test or ANOVA.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <p>If relationships appear linear, we may explore correlation
        coefficients or linear regression models to assess strength and
        direction.</p>
      </list-item>
    </list>
    <p>To support our findings, we will use ggplot2 in R to create clear
    and informative visualizations—such as boxplots, bar charts, or
    scatterplots—highlighting any significant trends or differences
    between the EPT-present and EPT-absent lake groups. Finally, missing
    data and uneven sampling will be carefully handled—either through
    exclusion of incomplete rows or imputation strategies, depending on
    the nature and extent of the gaps.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
</body>



<back>
</back>


</sub-article>

</article>